okay so the most ideal situation would
be if all instructions that we need to
execute could just go through the
pipeline in the same stage so basically
although all of them will end up
executing in the same cycle let's see an
example of this so we have a nice table
here and now we're going to have some
five instructions here so let's have
instruction so here's where we're going
to basically just have our instructions
and let's say that you know the first
instruction is an add instruction our
one equals R two plus three I'm gonna
draw it like this so that we don't have
to actually have the opcodes and
everything else clutter the screen and
then we have our four equals R 1 minus R
five and then we have X or R six equals
r 7x or 8 and then we will have our five
equals R eight times R nine and finally
we will have an ad of r 4 equals r 8 + r
9 so remember these are instructions not
actual C operations it's just a time
kind of showing them like this because
it's a more compact representations of
them and now let's see what happens in a
pipeline when we do this for a five
stage pipeline so in the first cycle so
this is cycle 1 this will be fetched and
this will be fetched and this will be
fetched and this will be fetched and
this will be fetched and then in cycle 2
we will decode this and read registers
and decode this and read registers and
decode this and read registers and so on
and now if you remember your five stage
pipeline the time comes to execute these
things so if we just get all five of
them here and execute them we will have
a very good CPI in reality what's going
to happen is that we are gonna
eventually write the results for all of
these things and if we had more
instructions here it wouldn't matter all
of this will be done in basically five
cycles so if we have five cycles for a
very large number of instructions the
CPI is going to be
five cycles for pretty much an infinite
number of instructions which is gonna be
very close to zero
so we get a CPI for zero which is very
good you know you are getting basically
zero almost zero cycles per instruction
so that's wonderful so what's wrong with
something like this well what's wrong
with it is that when we execute these
instructions what has happened is this
instruction in this instruction have
read registers at the same time remember
that the decode stage is also the read
register stage so what happens here is
we are here adding the R 2 plus R 3 and
here when we are writing we are really
writing R 1 ok but when we are adding
here I mean we are subtracting R 5 from
R 1 this R 1 here is not the R 1 that
this instruction is writing it's the R
one that we read before that instruction
managed to write anything so what's
wrong with this is that this first
instruction is going to execute
correctly but the second instruction
because we are executing it too early is
gonna basically read the R one from
before the first instruction so it
doesn't get the result of the first
instruction so the programmer who wrote
this wanted this R want to be this R 1
it was supposed to be like this but it
isn't and that means that we will have
to do something about this we cannot
just let instructions execute in the
same cycle we actually have to figure
out which ones can execute and which
ones cannot execute in the same cycle